{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "As part of Operation PANDORA, this organization tried to stir up anti-Semitism by mailing out racist fake pamphlets of right-wing Jewish organizations to civil rights organizations. This organization, which often collaborated with GRU, was led by Vladimir Kryuchkov, who helped plan an August 1991 coup. During the fall of the Berlin Wall, thousands of this organization’s files were burned by its officers, including Vladimir Putin. For ten points, name this Soviet intelligence agency.",
      "answer": [
        "KGB or Komitet Gosudarstvennoy Bezopasnosti",
        "Committee for State Security"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1894, kids accidentally started a fire under the stands in this city’s South End Grounds during a baseball game; the stadium and over 100 buildings were destroyed in the ensuing Great Roxbury Fire. This city lost over 60 acres worth of buildings in 12 hours after a warehouse on Kingston Street caught fire in 1872; that event was commemorated by its resident poet, Oliver Wendell Holmes Senior. In 1919, 21 people died after a storage tank burst and released a flood of molasses in, for ten points, what Massachusetts city?",
      "answer": "Boston"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s philosophy notably clashed with that of his contemporary, Antoine-Henri Jomini. One of this thinker’s students applied his philosophy at the Battle of Sedan; that student was Helmuth von Moltke. This man defined war as “the continuation of politics by other means,” and he described the confusion during “the fog of war” in his most famous work. For ten points, name this distinguished 19th century Prussian military strategist who wrote On War.",
      "answer": "Carl von Clausewitz"
    },
    {
      "question": "A student of this university named Sadie Tanner Mossell Alexander was the first African American woman to receive a Ph.D. A machine known as the “Giant Brain” was created at this university to calculate artillery firing tables; that early computer was ENIAC. The oldest medical school created in America is this university’s Perelman School, and it is also home to the first school of business, which is named after Joseph Wharton. For ten points, name this university founded by Benjamin Franklin in Philadelphia.",
      "answer": [
        "University of Pennsylvania",
        "UPenn"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist painted his friend Adrianus Jacobus Zuyderland dressed in blue with his head in his hands in At Eternity’s Gate, which shares its name with a 2018 film about this man. A landscape painting by this artist depicts a cypress tree and a crescent moon over the town of Saint-Remy. This artist of The Potato Eaters was hospitalized in Arles after injuring himself with a razor in 1888. For ten points, name this Dutch artist of Starry Night and Self Portrait with Bandaged Ear.",
      "answer": "Vincent Willem van Gogh"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to this battle, one side lost control of the Crampton and Turner passes during the Battle of South Mountain, nearly leading them to terminate their campaign. The losing side in this battle was hampered when Special Order 191 was discovered, wrapped in cigars, by the enemy. After a costly seizure of the Bloody Lane, George McClellan failed to press his advantage at this battle, leading Lincoln to replace him with Ambrose Burnside. For ten points, name this 1862 Maryland battle, the bloodiest single day of the Civil War.",
      "answer": "Battle of Antietam"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man returned to power after the scandal of the Lavon Affair, a botched false-flag bombing operation. Ahdut HaAvoda was founded by this man, who ordered the formation of Unit 101 and organized a massive airlift in Operation Magic Carpet as Prime Minister. During his second term, this man launched an invasion of Egypt, precipitating the Suez Crisis. For ten points, name this first prime minister of Israel.",
      "answer": "David Ben-Gurion"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rose to power after scheming with the Comte de Chevigny [comt de sheh-vi-nee] to remove Franc¸ois de Noyers [fran-swah de no-yay]. The League of the Rhine was formed by this man to limit Austrian power. This man concluded a war with Spain through the Treaty of the Pyrenees. This advisor barely survived a coup during the Fronde. For ten points, name this cardinal who acted as minister for Louis XIII and regent for Louis XIV.",
      "answer": "Cardinal Jules Mazarin"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a series of documents related to this scandal, William Rehnquist was referred to as “Renchburg;” the existence of those documents was publicly revealed by Alexander Butterfield. John Mitchell served 19 months in prison for his role in this scandal, which included Robert Bork’s agreement to fire special prosecutor Archibald Cox during the Saturday Night Massacre. The “Smoking Gun” tape was a key piece of evidence in, for ten points, what scandal that ended with Richard Nixon’s resignation?",
      "answer": "Watergate scandal"
    },
    {
      "question": "On this island, Marco Bragadin was infamously flayed alive after leading a heroic defense of Famagusta to delay the Ottoman Empire prior to Lepanto. Joan of England was captured by this island’s ruler Isaac Komnenos, prompting Richard I to invade it. This country’s modern Enosis movement prompted Operation Atilla, an invasion that helped extend this country’s Green Line of demarcation. For ten points, name this island country divided between Turkish and Greek zones.",
      "answer": "Cyprus"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this event, William Graham was criticized for memorializing members of the 5th Artillery who were killed on a dynamite-laced bridge while en route to stop this event. A rally to drum up support for this event was held at Blue Island, and it occurred despite an injunction from Richard Olney. When this event was deemed to interfere with federal mail, Grover Cleveland stepped in to end it. For ten points, name this 1894 Chicago strike against a namesake railway company.",
        "answer": "Pullman Strike"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This labor leader helped lead the Pullman Strike, years before he ran as a Socialist Party candidate for President from a jail cell.",
        "answer": "Eugene V. Debs"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ethnic group was involved in the Bambatha Rebellion in 1907, and it won a major military victory in 1879 after a solar eclipse appeared over the battlefield. This ethnic group was defeated at the Battle of Blood River, and this ethnic group’s king, Cetshwayo, was defeated at the Battle of Rorke’s Drift. For ten points, name this ethnic group, the victors at the Battle of Isandlwana, who ruled an empire in southern Africa until they were conquered by the British.",
        "answer": "amaZulu people"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Zulu king revamped their military procedures and died in 1828, well before the British conquest.",
        "answer": "Shaka Zulu or Shaka kaSenzangakhona"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city failed to annex a section of neighboring land after the Mafia organized it into an unincorporated town called Paradise. In 2010, a stock image of a landmark in this city was accidentally used for a Forever Stamp; that half-size replica of the Statue of Liberty stands outside the New York-New York Hotel. The construction of the Hoover Dam fueled the early growth of, for ten points, what most populous city in Nevada, a gambling resort town?",
        "answer": "Las Vegas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This American business tycoon purchased the Desert Inn in Las Vegas after refusing to leave one of its rooms. This famously reclusive man designed the Spruce Goose, a wooden plane.",
        "answer": "Howard Hughes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man befriended the Vestal Virgin Licinia to take her land. This man died in a skirmish after his assistant Octavius awkwardly tried to stop him from taking part in a peace negotiation. This man became wealthy by running a bucket brigade that would not help douse fires until homeowners paid him. This man’s victory at the Battle of the Siler River ended a slave revolt. A Parthian army killed this man and legendarily poured molten gold in the mouth of his corpse. For ten points, name this wealthy Roman who put down Spartacus’ revolt and formed the First Triumvirate with Julius Caesar and Pompey.",
        "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After Spartacus’ revolt was put down, Crassus ordered the crucifixion of six thousand slaves along this road from Rome to Brindisium.",
        "answer": "Appian Way or Via Appia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The phrase “pig in the python” titled a cultural history of this group, which was collectively named Time Person of the Year in 1966. Reduced adult supervision led this group’s successor to be called the “latchkey generation.” Lower mortgage requirements and the G.I. bill contributed to the rise of, for ten points, what American generation that was succeeded by Generation X and was born after World War II?",
        "answer": "Baby Boomers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aging curve of the Baby Boomers is often cited as a financial threat to Medicare, which was introduced as part of this set of domestic policies by Lyndon Johnson in 1964.",
        "answer": "Great Society"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This site was once believed to have been imported from Africa for use in healing, then transported from Mount Killaraus after a long battle. In 1915, this site was sold for 6000 pounds to Cecil Chubbs, who then donated it. This site is surrounded by “aubrey holes” speculated to have once contained bluestones; earlier historians speculated this site was a center of Druidic worship. For ten points, name this prehistoric site near Salisbury consisting of standing rocks.",
        "answer": "Stonehenge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Most of the bluestones of Stonehenge are made of dolerite, which is this type of rock. Ireland’s Giant’s Causeway is made of thousands of columns of basalt, another example of this type of rock.",
        "answer": "igneous rock"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This institution was created after Charles Lindbergh, Sr. helped inspire the creation of the Pujo Committee. James Reed’s decisive vote helped create this institution, resulting in his home state of Missouri being granted two of its 12 major branches. This agency was created by a bill introduced by Robert Owen and Carter Glass, each of whom chaired a congressional Banking and Currency Committee. A 1913 act created, for ten points, what central banking system of the US?",
        "answer": "Federal Reserve System"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man succeeded Janet Yellen as chair of the Federal Reserve in 2018, despite not having a PhD in Economics.",
        "answer": "Jerome Powell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a 1993 auction, a dummy named Ivan that was meant to test conditions prior to this man’s most famous undertaking sold for nearly $200,000. A cedar tree inspired the most famous callsign of this man, who exclaimed “Poyekhali!” In 1968, this man died while flying a MiG-15 after an air traffic controller misreported the weather, according to declassified files. After a mission of less than two hours in 1961, this man parachuted back to Earth. For ten points, name this cosmonaut who, aboard Vostok 1, became the first man in space.",
        "answer": "Yuri Alekseyevich Gagarin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1967, Gagarin was the backup pilot for the first manned flight of this Soviet spacecraft, which led to the first in-flight death in spaceflight history. This series of spacecraft is still in use by the Russian space program.",
        "answer": [
          "Soyuz",
          "Soyuz 1"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Modern Terrorism",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leader of al-Qaeda who was killed in Pakistan in 2011.",
          "answer": "Osama bin Laden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Building complex in New York that was destroyed on 9/11.",
          "answer": [
            "World Trade Center or WTC",
            "Twin Towers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American detention camp in Cuba where terrorists have been interrogated.",
          "answer": "Guantanamo Bay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Member of al-Qaeda who was the “architect” of 9/11 and the 2002 Bali nightclub bombing; he was captured in 2003.",
          "answer": [
            "Khalid Sheikh Mohammed",
            "KSM"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Form of water-based torture used by the US on members of al-Qaeda, including that 9/11 architect.",
          "answer": "waterboarding"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bio-toxin that was mailed to multiple news outlets and political figures in 2001.",
          "answer": "anthrax"
        },
        {
          "question": "American naval destroyer that was attacked by suicide bombers while in port in Yemen in 2000.",
          "answer": "USS Cole"
        },
        {
          "question": "Al-Qaeda operative who attempted to light plastic explosives in his shoe on a plane in December 2001.",
          "answer": "Richard Reid"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "European Fields",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Decisive August 1485 battle of the Wars of the Roses.",
          "answer": "Battle of Bosworth Field"
        },
        {
          "question": "English king who met Francis I at the Field of the Cloth of Gold and married six times.",
          "answer": "Henry VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Huns who was defeated at the Catalaunian Fields in the Battle of Chalons [sha-lone].",
          "answer": "Attila the Hun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Farming practice of planting fields of wheat, then beans, then nothing, to help replenish the soil.",
          "answer": "crop rotation"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which the poem “In Flanders Fields” was written after the Battle of Ypres [eep].",
          "answer": "World War I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paradise of Greek myth where heroes not sent to Hades were sent.",
          "answer": [
            "Elysian Fields",
            "Elysium"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Serbian territory where a 1389 battle of the Field of Blackbirds took place.",
          "answer": [
            "Kosovo",
            "Battle of Kosovo Polje"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "English city where an 1819 massacre took place in St. Peter’s Field.",
          "answer": "Manchester"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Religious Cities",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City that is home to the Temple Mount and the Dome of the Rock, the holiest city of Christianity and Judaism.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiest city of Islam, the destination of the hajj.",
          "answer": "Mecca"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion founded by Siddhartha Gautama, who gave his first sermon at Sarnath near Varanasi.",
          "answer": "Buddhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hometown of Jesus in the New Testament and capital of the Crusader-era Principality of Galilee.",
          "answer": "Nazareth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Plateau region claimed by China where Buddhists built monasteries in Lhasa.",
          "answer": "Tibet"
        },
        {
          "question": "Japanese city home to hundreds of Buddhist temples, including the Temple of the Golden Pavilion.",
          "answer": "Kyoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where the Shrine of the Bab, part of the Baha’i World Center, was built on Mount Carmel in 1891.",
          "answer": "Haifa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient Egyptian city, now a suburb of Cairo, where the sun god Atum was worshipped.",
          "answer": "Heliopolis"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This dynasty’s general Meng Tian defeated the Xiongnu [shee-ong-nu]. An attempt to assassinate a ruler of this dynasty involved putting lead at the end of a lute. This dynasty, whose chancellor (20 pts)",
        "Li Si instituted Legalist policies, was led by a man who supposedly drank an “elixir of life” that was just mercury. This dynasty, which followed the (10 pts)",
        "Warring States Period, was replaced by the Han Dynasty. A terracotta army was built for a ruler of, for ten points, what dynasty in which the Great Wall was built under the rule of Shi Huangdi?"
      ],
      "answer": "Qin Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This piece was commissioned for the price of 100 ducats, half paid in advance. Composition of this piece was delayed by time spent finishing La Clemenza di Tito and Die Zauberfloete. The figured bass line was all that was (20 pts)",
        "finished for some later movements of this piece, most of which was completed by Franz Sussmayr. Constanze, the wife of this work’s composer, tried to keep its unfinished nature a secret after the (10 pts)",
        "death of its composer in 1791. For ten points, name this musical piece that Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart believed he was composing for his own funeral."
      ],
      "answer": "Mozart’s Requiem mass in D minor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One leader of this political party tried to restore order with his “Back to Basics” campaign, which backfired after many of his ministers were caught in extramarital affairs. Another leader of this political party lost power in 1974 to a minority-power government led by (20 pts)",
        "Harold Wilson. Yet another leader of this party conducted a namesake program of privatizing government companies, was the target of the (10 pts)",
        "Brighton Hotel bombing, and was nicknamed “the Iron Lady.” Margaret Thatcher belonged to, for ten points, what British political party?"
      ],
      "answer": "Conservative and Unionist Party"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this irregular fighting force often used the “one slow, four quick” doctrine. Eddie Adams photographed a captain in this group who had recently killed a Lieutenant Colonel and his family; in that photo, the member of this group is wearing a flannel shirt and (20 pts)",
        "shot at point blank range by General Nguyen Loan [when loan]. This group led multiple attacks in January (10 pts)",
        "1968, striking the city of Hue [hway] and breaching the U.S. embassy in Saigon. For ten points, name this guerrilla fighting group that fought against the U.S. and South Vietnam during the Tet Offensive."
      ],
      "answer": "Viet Cong or National Liberation Front"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While Aristophanes of Byzantium led one of these facilities, he invented the diacritical marks used in the Greek language; Aristarchus of Samothrace later led that one of these facilities. When one of these facilities was excavated in (20 pts)",
        "Ashurbanipal’s palace, its discoveries were mixed with tablets found in Sennacherib’s palace, rendering the true discovery location of the (10 pts)",
        "Epic of Gilgamesh a mystery. For ten points, name this type of location that Julius Caesar burned in Alexandria, causing the loss of thousands of papyrus scrolls and their educational contents."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ancient library",
        "Library of Alexandria",
        "Library of Ashurbanipal after his name is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The president who authorized this agreement wrote a letter outlining his diplomatic strategy to Governor James Gerrard of Kentucky. Fran¸cois de Barb´e-Marbois [bar-bay mar-bwah] was a key negotiator of this agreement, which arose after an (20 pts)",
        "insurrection on Saint Domingue [sahn doh-meeng]. Talleyrand objected to this plan, which resulted in the (10 pts)",
        "Lewis and Clark Expedition surveying its central land area. The size of the United States was doubled by, for ten points, what 1803 purchase of French land under Thomas Jefferson?"
      ],
      "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The weekly Torah reading is divided into this many aliyahs. In the first part of the book of Revelation, the author writes letters to this many churches in Asia Minor. Jericho’s (20 pts)",
        "walls fell after this many days of marching, and King David had this many brothers. The Passover feast lasts this many days, and this is the number of (10 pts)",
        "lamps on the Temple of Jerusalem’s menorah. For ten points, give this number of the day God rested in the first Genesis narrative, which is also the number of deadly sins."
      ],
      "answer": "seven"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s deformed son was sent to the monastery of Pru¨m after his plot to overthrow this man was discovered. This man’s mother Bertrada assisted him in his struggle against his brother, and he divorced his (20 pts)",
        "Lombard wife Desiderata before conquering Italy. This ruler, who put down the Great Saxon Revolt after converting them to Christianity, had his forces defeated at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Roncevaux Pass, the source of the Song of Roland. For ten points, name this Frankish king crowned Emperor of the Romans on Christmas Day 800."
      ],
      "answer": "Charlemagne"
    }
  ]
}